(Clicking)
(نقر)
I was born with bilateral retinoblastoma,
وُلدت مصابًا بورم أرومة الشبكية الثنائي،
retinal cancer.
سرطان في شبكية العين.
My right eye was removed
تمت إزالة عيني اليمنى
at seven months of age.
عند بلوغي سبعة أشهر.
I was 13 months when they removed my left eye.
كان عمري 13 شهرًا عندما قاموا بإزالة عيني اليسرى.
The first thing I did upon awakening from that last surgery
وأول شيء قمت به عند استيقاظي من تلك العملية الأخيرة
was to climb out of my crib
كان التسلق إلى خارج سريري
and begin wandering around the intensive care nursery,
والسير في أرجاء غرفة العناية المكثقة،
probably looking for the one who did this to me.
ربما للبحث عمن فعل هذا بي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Evidently, wandering around the nursery
بصراحة، لم يكن السير في أرجاء الغرفة
was not a problem for me without eyes.
يمثل مشكلة بالنسبة لي دون عيوني.
The problem was getting caught.
كانت المشكلة هي القبض عليّ.
It's impressions about blindness
إن الانطباعات حول العمى
that are far more threatening
هي أكثر إخافة
to blind people than the blindness itself.
بالنسبة للأشخاص العُمي من العمى نفسه.
Think for a moment about your own impressions of blindness.
فكروا للحظة في انطباعاتكم حول العمى.
Think about your reactions when I first came onto the stage,
فكروا عن ردة فعلكم عندما وقفت على المنصة،
or the prospect of your own blindness,
أو تنبؤ بإصابتكم بالعمى،
or a loved one going blind.
أو أن أحدا ممن تحبونهم أصيب بالعمى.
The terror is incomprehensible to most of us,
يصعب تفسير حالة الرعب بالنسبة لمعظمنا،
because blindness
بسبب الاعتقاد بأن العمى
is thought to epitomize ignorance and unawareness,
يمثل الجهل وعدم الوعي،
hapless exposure to the ravages of the dark unknown.
وتعرض التعساء لويلات المجهول المظلم.
How poetic.
يا له من أمر شاعري.
Fortunately for me, my parents were not poetic.
ولحسن حظي فإن والداي ليسا بشاعريين.
They were pragmatic.
كانا عمليان.
They understood that ignorance and fear were but matters of the mind,
هما فهما أن الجهل والخوف لم يكونا سوى أمور عقلية،
and the mind is adaptable.
وأن العقل قابل للتكيف.
They believed that I should grow up
هما آمنا بأن عليّ أن أكبر
to enjoy the same freedoms and responsibilities as everyone else.
لأستمتع بنفس الحريات والمسؤوليات كجميع الأشخاص الآخرين.
In their own words, I would move out --
وحسب تعبيرها، بإمكاني أن أخرج --
which I did when I was 18 --
وهذا ما فعلته عندما كنت في الثامنة عشرة --
I will pay taxes --
سأقوم بدفع الضرائب --
thanks -- (Laughter) --
شكرًا -- (ضحك) --
and they knew the difference between love and fear.
وقدعرفا الفرق بين الحب والخوف.
Fear immobilizes us in the face of challenge.
فالخوف يشل حركتنا في مواجهة التحديات.
They knew that blindness would pose a significant challenge.
هما عرفا أن العمى سيشكل تحديًا كبيرًا.
I was not raised with fear.
لم أكبر مع الخوف.
They put my freedom first before all else,
وضعا حريتي قبل كل شيء آخر،
because that is what love does.
لأن هذا ما يفعله الحب.
Now, moving forward, how do I manage today?
الآن، بالمضي قدمًا، كيف أدبر أمري اليوم؟
The world is a much larger nursery.
العالم غرفة أكبر بكثير.
Fortunately, I have my trusty long cane,
ولحسن الحظ، لدي عصاتي الطويلة الموثوقة،
longer than the canes used by most blind people.
أطول من العصي التي يستخدمها أغلب العِميّ.
I call it my freedom staff.
أطلق عليها اسم طاقم حريتي.
It will keep me, for example,
ستمنعني، على سبيل المثال،
from making an undignified departure from the stage. (Laughter)
من القيام بخروج غير لائق من المنصة. (ضحك)
I do see that cliff edge.
أرى بالفعل تلك الحافة المنحدرة.
They warned us earlier that every imaginable mishap
حذرونا سابقًا بأن أي حادث مؤسف يمكن تخيله
has occurred to speakers up here on the stage.
قد حصل للمتحدثين هنا على المنصة.
I don't care to set a new precedent.
لايهمني إن أعدت القيام بسابقة أخرى.
But beyond that,
ولكن فيما عدا ذلك،
many of you may have heard me clicking as I came onto the stage --
العديد منكم سمعوني أنقر بينما كنت أصعد إلى المنصة --
(Clicking) --
(نقر) --
with my tongue.
بلساني.
Those are flashes of sound
هذه ومضات من الصوت
that go out and reflect from surfaces all around me,
تخرج وتعكسها الأسطح من حولي،
just like a bat's sonar,
مثل تقنية تحديد موقع الصدى عندالخفاش،
and return to me with patterns, with pieces of information,
وتعود إليّ مع قوالب، مع معلومات،
much as light does for you.
أشبه بما يفعله الضوء لك.
And my brain, thanks to my parents,
وعقلي، بفضل أبواي،
has been activated to form images in my visual cortex,
قد تنشط لتشكيل الصور في قشرتي البصرية،
which we now call the imaging system,
التي ندعوها الآن باسم نظام التصوير،
from those patterns of information, much as your brain does.
من قوالب المعلومات هذه، كما يفعل دماغك.
I call this process flash sonar.
أطلق على هذه العلمية اسم الصدى المتوهج.
It is how I have learned to see through my blindness,
إنها الطريقة التي تعلمت بها الرؤية من خلال العمى،
to navigate my journey
للإبحار في رحلتي
through the dark unknowns of my own challenges,
من خلال ظلمات المجهول من تحدياتي،
which has earned me the moniker
ما قد حقق لي لقب
"the remarkable Batman."
"باتمان المثير للإعجاب."
Now, Batman I will accept.
الآن، سأقبل لقب باتمان.
Bats are cool. Batman is cool.
الخفافيش رائعة. باتمان رائع.
But I was not raised to think of myself as in any way remarkable.
ولكنني لم أنشأ لأرى نفسي مثيرًا للإعجاب من أي ناحية.
I have always regarded myself much like anyone else
لقد اعتبرت نفسي دومًا كأي شخص آخر
who navigates the dark unknowns of their own challenges.
يبحر في ظلمات المجهول من تحدياته.
Is that so remarkable?
هل هذا مثيرٌ جدًا للإعجاب؟
I do not use my eyes, I use my brain.
لا أستعمل عيناي، أنا أستعمل عقلي.
Now, someone, somewhere,
الآن، أحد ما في مكان ما
must think that's remarkable, or I wouldn't be up here,
يفكر بأن هذا أمرٌ مثيرٌ للإعجاب، وإلا لما كنت واقفًا هنا،
but let's consider this for a moment.
ولكن دعونا لوهلة نأخذ هذا بعين الاعتبار.
Everyone out there
كلكم هناك،
who faces or who has ever faced a challenge,
من يواجه أو سبق له أن واجه تحديًا
raise your hands.
فليرفع يديه.
Whoosh. Okay.
حسنًا.
Lots of hands going up, a moment, let me do a head count.
تُرفع الكثير من الأيدي، لحظة، دعوني أقوم بعد الأشخاص.
(Clicking)
(نقر)
This will take a while. (Clicking) (Laughter)
هذا سيستغرق وقتًا. (نقر) (ضحك)
Okay, lots of hands in the air.
حسنًا، العديد من الأيدي مرفوعة.
Keep them up. I have an idea.
أبقوها مرفوعة. لديّ فكرة.
Those of you who use your brains to navigate these challenges,
هؤلاء منكم الذين يستخدمون عقولهم للإبحار في هذه التحديات،
put your hands down.
أنزلوا أيديكم.
Okay, anyone with your hands still up
حسنًا، أي واحد منكم لا زال يرفع يديه
has challenges of your own. (Laughter)
لديه تحديات تخصه. (ضحك)
So we all face challenges,
إذًا فنحن جميعًا نواجه تحديات،
and we all face the dark unknown,
وكلنا يواجه ظلمات المجهول،
which is endemic to most challenges, which is what most of us fear, okay?
وهو أمر يصاحب معظم التحديات، وهو ما يخافه أغلبيتنا، موافقون؟
But we all have brains
ولكننا جميعًا نملك أدمغة
that allow us, that activate to allow us
تسمح لنا، تتنشط لتسمح لنا بالإبحار
to navigate the journey through these challenges. Okay?
في الرحلة عبر هذه التحديات. موافقون؟
Case in point: I came up here
مثال للتوضيح: أتيت للأعلى هنا
and -- (Clicking) -- they wouldn't tell me
و -- (نقر) -- ولم يخبروني
where the lectern was.
أين توجد منضدة القراءة.
So you can't trust those TED folks.
إذًا لا يمكنك الوثوق بجماعة TED هؤلاء.
"Find it yourself," they said.
قالوا لي: "قم بإيجادها بنفسك."
So -- (Laughter)
إذًا -- (ضحك)
And the feedback for the P.A. system is no help at all.
والتغذية الراجعة لنظام الإذاعة عديم الفائدة.
So now I present to you a challenge.
إذًا أنا أقدم لك الآن تحديًا.
So if you'd all close your eyes for just a moment, okay?
لذا لو تقومون جميعًا بإغلاق أعينكم للحظة فقط، موافقون؟
And you're going to learn a bit of flash sonar.
ستتعلمون قليلًا عن السونار الفلاشي.
I'm going to make a sound.
سأقوم بعمل صوت.
I'm going to hold this panel in front of me, but I'm not going to move it.
سأمسك بهذه اللوحة التي أمامي، ولكنني لن أحركها.
Just listen to the sound for a moment.
فقط استعموا إلى الصوت لوهلة.
Shhhhhhhhhh.
ششششش.
Okay, nothing very interesting.
حسنًا، لا شيء مثيرللاهتمام.
Now, listen to what happens to that same exact sound
الآن، استمعوا لما يطرأ على ذلك الصوت نفسه
when I move the panel.
عندما أقوم بتحريك اللوحة.
Shhhhhhhhhhh. (Pitch getting higher and lower)
ششششش. (طبقة الصوت تعلو وتنخفض)
You do not know the power of the dark side.
أنتم لا تعلمون مدى قوة الجانب المظلم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I couldn't resist.
لم أستطع المقاومة.
Okay, now keep your eyes closed
حسنًا، أبقوا عيونكم مغلقة
because, did you hear the difference?
الآن، هل سمعتم الفرق؟
Okay. Now, let's be sure.
حسنًا. الآن، دعونا نتأكد.
For your challenge,
بالنسبة للتحدي خاصتكم،
you tell me, just say "now" when you hear the panel start to move.
أخبروني، قولوا "الآن" فقط عندما تسمعون اللوحة وهي تبدأ بالحركة.
Okay? We'll relax into this.
موافقون؟ سنسترخي في سماع هذا.
Shhhhhhh.
شششششش.
Audience: Now. Daniel Kish: Good. Excellent.
الجمهور: الآن. دانيال كيش: جيد. ممتاز.
Open your eyes.
افتحوا أعينكم.
All right. So just a few centimeters,
حسنًا. إذًا لسنتيمترات قليلة فقط،
you would notice the difference.
بإمكانكم ملاحظة الفرق.
You've experienced sonar.
لقد جربتم نظام تحديد موقع الصدى(سونار).
You'd all make great blind people. (Laughter)
ستجعلون من أنفسكم عُميًا عظماء. (ضحك)
Let's have a look at what can happen
لنلقي نظرة على ما سيحدث
when this activation process
عندما تُعطى عملية التنشيط هذه
is given some time and attention.
بعض الوقت والانتباه.
(Video) Juan Ruiz: It's like you guys can see with your eyes
(فيديو) جوان روز: كأن بإمكانكم يا أصدقاء الرؤية بأعينكم
and we can see with our ears.
وبإمكاننا أن نرى بآذاننا.
Brian Bushway: It's not a matter of enjoying it more or less,
رجل: إنها ليست مسألة استمتاع أكثر أو أقل،
it's about enjoying it differently.
إنه استمتاع بشكل مختلف.
Shawn Marsolais: It goes across. DK: Yeah.
امرأة: إنها مستقيمة. دانيال كيش: نعم.
SM: And then it's gradually coming back down again.
امرأة: ومن ثم تنخفض تدريجيًا مرة أخرى.
DK: Yes! SM: That's amazing.
دانيال كيش: نعم! امرأة: ذلك مدهش.
I can, like, see the car. Holy mother!
بإمكاني رؤية السيارة مثلًا. أمر رائع.
J. Louchart: I love being blind.
رجل 2: أحب كوني أعمى.
If I had the opportunity, honestly, I wouldn't go back to being sighted.
بصدق، لو كانت لدي الفرصة، لن أعود ثانية لأكون بصيرًا.
JR: The bigger the goal, the more obstacles you'll face,
رجل 3: كلما كبر الهدف، كلما زادت العوائق التي تواجهها،
and on the other side of that goal
وعلى الجانب الآخر من ذلك الهدف
is victory.
يوجد الانتصار.
[In Italian]
[بالإيطالية]
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
DK: Now, do these people look terrified?
دانيال كيش: الآن، هل يبدو هؤلاء الأشخاص خائفون؟
Not so much.
ليس كثيرًا.
We have delivered activation training
لقد قدمنا تمارين تنشيط
to tens of thousands of blind and sighted people from all backgrounds
لعشرات الآلاف من الأشخاص العمي والمبصرين من جميع الخلفيات
in nearly 40 countries.
في ما يقارب 40 دولة.
When blind people learn to see,
عندما يتعلم العُمي الرؤية،
sighted people seem inspired
يبدو المبصرون ملهمين
to want to learn to see their way better, more clearly, with less fear,
ليريدوا تعلم رؤية طريقهم بشكل أفضل، أكثر وضوحًا، مع خوف أقل،
because this exemplifies the immense capacity within us all
لأن هذا يمثل الطاقة الهائلة التي بداخلنا
to navigate any type of challenge, through any form of darkness,
للإبحار في أي نوع من التحديات، من خلال أي نوع من الظلام،
to discoveries unimagined
إلى اكتشافات لم نتصورها
when we are activated.
عند تنشيطنا.
I wish you all a most activating journey.
أتمنى لكم جميعًا رحلة تنشيطية جدًا.
Thank you very much.
شكرًا جزيلًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Chris Anderson: Daniel, my friend.
كريس أندرسون: دانيال، صديقي.
As I know you can see, it's a spectacular standing ovation at TED.
أعلم أنك ترى، أهناك تصفيق ووقوف للجمهور بحفاوة بالغة في TED.
Thank you for an extraordinary talk.
شكرًا لك لمحادثتك المذهلة.
Just one more question about your world, your inner world that you construct.
فقط هناك سؤال آخر عن عالمك، عالمك الداخلي الذي تقوم ببنائه.
We think that we have things in our world that you as a blind person don't have,
نعتقد أننا نملك أشياء في عالمنا أنت كأعمى لا تملكها،
but what's your world like?
ولكن كيف يبدو عالمك؟
What do you have that we don't have?
ما الذي تملكه أنت ولا نملكه نحن؟
DK: Three hundred and sixty-degree view,
دانيال كيش: رؤية بزاوية 360 درجة،
so my sonar works about as well behind me as it does in front of me.
إذًا فتقنيتي لتحديد الموقع بالصدى تعمل بنفس الكفاءة خلفي كما أمامي.
It works around corners.
فهي تعمل حول الزوايا.
It works through surfaces.
تعمل من خلال الأسطح.
Generally, it's kind of a fuzzy three-dimensional geometry.
وبشكل عام، فهي نوع من الهندسة المشوشة ثلاثية الأبعاد.
One of my students, who has now become an instructor,
أحد تلاميذي، الذي أصبح الآن معلمًا،
when he lost his vision, after a few months
عندما فقد بصره،بعد أشهر قليلة
he was sitting in his three story house
كان يجلس في بيته ذي الثلاث طوابق
and he realized that he could hear everything going on throughout the house:
وأدرك أن بإمكانه سماع كل ما يحدث في أرجاء المنزل:
conversations, people in the kitchen, people in the bathroom,
المحادثات، الناس في المطبخ، الناس في الحمام،
several floors away, several walls away.
على بعد عدة شقق، على بعد عدة جدران.
He said it was something like having x-ray vision.
قال بأن ذلك كان كامتلاك رؤية بأشعة إكس.
CA: What do you picture that you're in right now?
كريس أندرسون: ما الحالة التي ترى فيها نفسك الآن؟
How do you picture this theater?
كيف ترى هذا المسرح؟
DK: Lots of loudspeakers, quite frankly.
دانيال كيش: الكثير من مكبرات الصوت، هذا واضح جدًا.
It's interesting. When people make a sound,
هذا مثير للاهتمام. عندما يصدر الناس أصواتًا،
when they laugh, when they fidget, when they take a drink or blow their nose
عندما يضحكون، عندما يتململون، عندما يتناولون شرابًا أو يرفعون صوتهم
or whatever, I hear everything.
أو ما إلى ذلك، أسمع كل شيء.
I hear every little movement that every single person makes.
أسمع كل حركة صغيرة يقوم بإصدارها أي شخص.
None of it really escapes my attention,
لا شيء منها يفلت من انتباهي،
and then, from a sonar perspective,
وبعد ذلك من منظور تقنية السونار،
the size of the room, the curvature of the audience around the stage,
حجم القاعة، التفاف الحضور حول المنصة،
it's the height of the room.
إنه ارتفاع القاعة.
Like I say, it's all that kind of three-dimensional surface geometry
كما أقول،هذا كله نوع من هندسة الأسطح ثلاثية الأبعاد
all around me.
حولي.
CA: Well, Daniel, you have done a spectacular job
كريس أندرسون: دانيال، لقد قمت بعمل رائع
of helping us all see the world in a different way.
في مساعدتناعلى رؤية العالم بطريقة مختلفة.
Thanks so much for that, truly. DK: Thank you.
شكرًا جزيلًا على ذلك، حقًا. دانيال كيش: شكرًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)